Guide to the William Morris Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
William Morris collection
1870-1895
GEN MSS 45
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.42
(1 box)
The collection consists of seven letters written by William Morris to friends and acquaintances, and a group of autograph manuscripts by Morris. One manuscript, "The Wood Beyond the World," is accompanied by a drawing made for the book by Sir Edward Coley Burne-Jones, and two impressions of the resulting engraving. Also present is a letter to the American collector Dean Sage regarding one of the manuscripts.
Morris, William, 1834-1896
Existence and Location of Copies
Portions of the collection were microfilmed and appear on Beinecke Library Vault Film 524.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired from various sources, 1943-1975. Source information is recorded at the folder level in the contents list. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
William Morris (1834-1896)
William Morris was an English designer, artist, writer, and socialist associated with the Pre-Raphaelite Brotherhood and the English Arts and Crafts Movement.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of seven letters written by William Morris to friends and acquaintances, and a group of autograph manuscripts by him. One manuscript, "The Wood Beyond the World," is accompanied by a drawing made for the book by Sir Edward Coley Burne-Jones, and two impressions of the resulting engraving.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Letters, 1870-1891. II. Writings, 1870-1895.
Authors, English -- 19th century; English literature -- 19th century; Drawings (visual works) -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Engravings (prints) -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Authors -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Burne-Jones, Edward Coley, 1833-1898; Eiríkr Magnússon, 1833-1913; Ellis, Havelock, 1859-1939; Morris, William, 1834-1896; Sage, Dean, 1841-1902; Shannon, Charles, 1863-1937
- Letters, 1870-1891; Series I; 7
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  - To "Dear Sir"; autograph letter, signed, 1870 Feb 25 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Custodial History
    From the library of Bishop Charles A. Clough (Yale 1926); gift of Mrs. Clifton Clough.
  - To "Mr. Craik"; autograph letter, signed, 1877 Jan 11 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Purchased from Arthur Rogers on the Phelps Fund, 1956.
  - To "Dear Comrade"; autograph letter, signed, 1888 Apr 26 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Removed from J. W. Mackail, The Life of William Morris (London: 1899); purchased from Stonehill on the John Ewing Durand Memorial Fund, 1949.
  - To Havelock Ellis; autograph letter, signed, 1890 Jun 2 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Purchased from Stonehill on the Hubert Amer McGuire Memorial Fund, 1961.
  - To "Dear Sirs"; autograph letter, signed, 1891 Feb 2 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Gift of Elizabeth Wade White and Evelyn V. Holahan in memory of Carl Purlington Rollins, 1974.
  - To "My dear Nichol"; autograph letter, signed, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Purchased from Charles Hamilton on the Francis O. Matthiesen Fund, 1957.
  - To Charles Hazelwood Shannon; autograph letter, signed, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    General note
    Accompanied by two half-tone images of Morris, his calling card and his book stamp
    Purchased from Stonehill on the Starling W. Childs Library Fund, 1958.
- Writings, 1870-1895; Series II; 5
  - "The Story of Harald the Hardredy"; autograph manuscript translation from the Icelandic by Eiríkr Magnússon, circa 1870 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Purchased from Stonehill on the Frank Altschul Fund, 1946.
    With autograph corrections and alterations by Morris, and autograph English translations of 89 verses of Icelandic poems.
  - "Hopes and Fears for Art"; autograph manuscript, 1878-1893 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Purchased from Scribner on the John Ewing Durand Memorial Fund, 1943.
    Four lectures delivered in Birmingham, London, and Nottingham: "The Art of the People" (23 p.); The Beauty of Life" (31 p.); Making the Best of It" (35 p.); The Prospects of Architecture in Civilization" (38 p.).
    Also bound in: "Westminster Abbey"; autograph manuscript (12 p.) accompanied by printed pamphlet Concerning Westminster Abbey (London: Society for the Protection of Ancient Buildings, 1893)
    Also bound in: "Arts and Crafts"; autograph manuscript, signed (4 p.), preface to Arts and Crafts Essays by Members of the Arts and Crafts Exhibition Society (London: Rivington, Percival & Co., 1893).
  - "What is to Happen Next?"; autograph manuscript, signed, circa 1886 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Text of an article which appeared in The Commonweal, no. 28 (June 24, 1886), p. 129.
    Accompanied by a typed letter from Dodd, Mead & Co., to Dean Sage (November 19, 1901).
  - "The Wood Beyond the World"; autograph manuscript, signed, 1894-1895 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
    Bequest of Norman Holmes Pearson (Yale 1932), 1975.
    With autograph corrections and additions (139 p.); published in 1894 by the Kelmscott Press.
    Includes a graphite drawing by Sir Edward Coley Burne-Jones and two prints of the engraving after the drawing: a proof on paper and an impression on parchment. Also present is an autograph draft of a letter by Morris (July 16, 1895) to the editor of The Spectator regarding a review of The Wood Beyond the World published in that periodical.